all right hello and welcome everyone it
is July
7th 2023 and we are in the first
introductory session of the course
active inference for the social sciences
this is going to be a really exciting
course and journey that we're all going
to join and co-create together
thank you
complex systems and feedbacks
with cyber physical systems will be a
theme we told you it would be
I will pass now to Avil for the
introductory session if you're watching
live please feel free to write any
comments or questions in the chat and
I'll relay them at the end
on to the lecture thanks Evel
go for it
foreign
okay cool
so I'm available I uh organized against
the course I uh
had the ID and uh worked on the
curriculum
uh do you see this slides well
looks good and just make sure to close
the YouTube video or mute it
so hi uh
some issue okay cool
okay I did not know how to do that
so
uh this is the introduction session of
the course Very unsurprisingly my name
is Regina kerou I am a founding member
of careless research and I am a
non-funding member of Q inference lab
which uh co-organize the course
and first I will basically present the
teaching team so we have Danielle which
is uh with us which is a PSG ecology and
evolution studying and we have your in
Eco Evo kind of way
who is a president and co-founder of the
activator Institutes and who is
interested in Hamilton's art philosophy
and cognitive security
then we have done which is also here
with us which is a second year prg
candidate in philosophical University of
Sussex which like me
interested in
um for e-cognition which is um embodied
inactive embedded and extended cognition
we don't need to get into that now he
will explain to you and in predictive
processing and which is basically
working on the cognitive science of
technology and then we are the people
who are not here today which are Mao Al
Bahasa tsg candidate in the cognitive
Computing at University
which is head of product Innovation and
research at versus private sector
research lab in Ai and the mathematics
of AI which specializes in Wildlife
inference so we were working on right
now script Theory which you will extend
maybe I will talk a bit of it today but
she will be the one who explains what
Chris criteria is to you and modular
activity artificial intelligence
and we have Learning Center
also appearances
also in philosophy but in Wollongong I
believe this is how you say it's in
Australia which is centered in
Philadelphia mind and in the status of
information processing as the term is
used in cognitive science
and then there is me so I made a career
timeline because when I talk about what
I did people get confused I did a
physics math I did engineering I did
cognitive science I did research in
ecology and evolution and in the Masters
in a complex system physics and uh I did
like one year apparently given my
timeline or two no more than more to us
independent research as a part of keros
research and as part of the French
society of Economics before I started
the phdn ring now which is a
something about the relation between
mind and material culture we will get
into that at some point
and the question motivation I have are
um essentially describing the relation
between phenomenology so the way we're
experience the world and the physical
reality which I have The Fringe view
that somehow of criminology is
constructive of physical reality which
could have weak and some interpretation
I subscribe to both
I'm trying maybe more importantly here
to uh explain or at least describe how
Social Security life format to say the
irregularities that analyze social life
humans through life are constructed
which is hard and I'm trying to uh well
build a research that is effective at
doing you know knowledge not word piles
through our work in chaos research
so these are specific reference you will
get the slides at some point I guess I
will publish them on the website and
then we'll be able to check it out if
this is of interest to you
so let us get on the actual relevant
content so the what we are going for
here is basically explain the very basic
the merge of the course explain
um how it's of relevance how the
framework we proposes of free events to
social science and present a few case
studies you know make the case and then
we will talk about course layout but
this is pretty quick
so
first I'd like to talk about the
explanation of cultural Dynamics what
does explaining cultural Dynamics even
mean it depends who talks
there are many many many many many many
types or views on what is scientific
explanation
I say we can cluster them in three broad
categories one is a numerological so
it's about laws and what it does is to
take regularities just say here is this
regularity
and consider that these statements so
the law has an explanatory capacity
toward the regularity
so for example for those of you who are
familiar with um
the work of
and I forget names
Foundation the foundations
Trilogy this is pretty close to what
they call Psycho history so basically
trying to do trying to find laws of
behavior and using them to predict
history in a regular lawful way
then we have mechanical explanation
which are more typical of the life
science and what we do in mechanical
explanation is to look at the structure
of a system and model the structure and
try to use this model to you know
predict specific regularities that are
of Interest
and you have a approach to social sense
that is I'd say quite close to that
which is cloud Linux
logical side but still is centered on
Dynamics and mechanisms and explanation
by calling on to structure in specific
societies
and then you have a functional
explanation which asks what constraints
exists so that the system does what it
is understand those here again you will
also use a lot of contextual modeling
very often
evolutionary Game Theory so
simulation where we suppose that agent
can have specific traits and those that
reproduce more or that have more Fitness
you know give their threats around
and you have the discipline field of
study of cultural Evolution that does
that very concretely by just asking you
know how could you evolve so what
cultural threats can get more Fitness
and be transmitted a very evolutionary
centered approach to social change
so uh to send all of this up basically
we explained things by calling on to
regularities always
and we can't talk about regularities in
the phenomenology so what the system
does in of itself in this structure that
is no language system activity or in the
function that is the constraints that
exist over what the Sim does
and
you have a specific brand of explanatory
strategies that try to legify behavior
to make nomological lawful explanation
of human behavior and of such a cultural
change
and it's not
immediately evident how they do that how
they think it's coherent ideally to
begin with because well humans learn
cultural challenge so what laws could
they be
in um
in a field where which is changing with
time always
so
in my opinion it is a more question of
you know rhetorics than of epistemology
because I do not think the answer is
coherent
the answer is as far as I'm concerned
that people they just
refi regularities that are observed in
experimental settings often that are
quite heavily fabricated
as kind of cognitive laws of behavior
and because
those people usually agree in spirit to
the mechanical kind of explanation they
talk about cognitive mechanism or mental
processes but only insofar that those
mechanisms or processes are explanatory
of cognitive laws they do not do the
work of you know looking at the
structure and function of the systems
that I just claim there must be a
mechanism that explains the vague law
that I have observed over 20 people that
came to my lab
and these laws they are assumed to scale
for the inclination of social activity
and
so you have it you have the recipe for
universal law of social change
and the basically the whole
arguments stands on the idea that you
have a presentation or mental processes
or a cognitive mechanism that somehow
entail the subjects behavior is regular
through time and between individuals
and you never have the work that would
actually in any capacity prove it for
reasons that we will not get into
because it will get math ready and renty
so
if uh the rules and regularities of
human behavior can change to learning
through cultural Evolution through
whatnot
how can we exactly model or explain or
even describe this agency
um this is not doable in an homological
framework because when we do natural
laws we look at regularities we claim
here is alone this regularity is a low
so it explains that you know it exists
and uh this is a circle because
as far as I'm concerned it's a check log
reasoning like the regularities explain
the regularities which explain the
regularities there is no way out of this
you can recurse this all day long this
the only fact that you observe the thing
is restonation for the thing this is not
hopefully how we do things in science
any other
process of explanation that is more
complete if you look at uh
structure and function written large you
can look at a specific system which has
specific structure and you can look at
what the system does well the function
of the system and at the specific time
and you can look out at how this
function this activity shapes the system
later on at t plus one you can have uh
you know developmental approach to
things that is internal health system
unfold how they learn how they evolve
through time like that is doable that
there is no law against that and it
could actually work so yeah let's do
that
um let's explain natural Fernand by
describing how the underlying structure
work but also by trying to explain how
it's brought about how resistance
activity explain the way it's
takes shape through time
so a claim that we will make here that
is itself
it could be contentious but we don't
have to look at why it is not
Philippines here
is that active in France which is a
specific new trendy theory of human
cognition
can actually explain how regularities in
relying social activity be constructed
Through Time
and let us look at what active Insurance
says precisely so there is we won't look
at the math ever we won't look here at
the specifics of the theory the only
thing we are going for is to prove that
this Theory indeed does what I think it
does which is explained or at least
described in a non-trivial way the
evolution of you know social
regularities
so
if active inference framework is true
then cognitive agents perceive the world
through expectation
they have developed about the world so
perception is an active process
I do not perceive things with my eyes
and compute higher and higher level of
traits of what I saw I basically expect
things in front of me and I will
actively look at the things that are
most likely to inform me
and something that is critical about
this framework is that
the prediction it also underlies action
or policies so let's say trajectory of
action that inact I will do the action
that I believe I'm more likely to do I
will do that in virtue of me believing
I am more likely to do this action oops
so
in that framework active in France you
understood as a process of an action
of a specific model
that is causally shaped both by an
agents Dynamics and environment Dynamics
and this relation well brings a model
that corresponds in abstract way to the
um
structure
of the Dynamics of the relation and this
module I can also look at um
look at it in a way more concrete
concrete sense in that it is what in the
lives what drives the edge and dynamic
you have a duality between the Dynamics
and the epistemic mantle states that we
put that we project that we can observe
in the learning
so
a very important
aspect of this is that it dissolves
entirely agency as we would understand
the term
there is no distinct step of perception
which informs the agent and what action
on what the world is like
and based on which the agents decide
freely what action it will take
there is a constant prediction of what
is going to happen
and this is enacted by the agent both
through perception and action so the
what drives
decision here what drives a generally
the flow that drive that analyze the
Urgent behavior is the Urgent self model
and that is that has interesting
consequences
so I have notifications so we'll look at
them
sorry
what let me drink I will drink I need to
drink
so one consequence of this um
formalism is that normativity so the
values
and Norms it's hard to go around that
word that drive Behavior they are not
you know in the brain they are not
something that the Urgent abstractly
relates to they are embedded in the very
process in which the agent understand
and gojis and navigates the world
and this is a variable event for a human
cultural Evolution because well we are
cultural creatures we learn
expectation about each other
uh both explicitly by you know looking
at how people do things and then
expecting them to do the same things
again
and implicitly through the very process
by which we
um
relates to other people like Norms like
language
and the way you look at this
this um
this learning three Mission it can be it
can be reduced essentially because of
the properties of active infrons to uh
what people call regimes of attention so
the way I pay attention to things the
specific
things I will look at in my process of
understanding and navigating the world
um
the Flow by which admined that is the
same thing as a set of value and a set
of expectations
so
what is important here is that
normativity and values and things like
that they are
uh embedded in my cognition in a much
more basic way than you know conscious
self-reflection also of course conscious
reflection can inform that flow it is uh
embedded in the shared expectation I
have with other people and there is no
Valentino result that I can actually be
reflexive about it because well the web
predicts things it's based on the
statistical regularities that have seen
in the world and because the way I pay
attention it's
you know entailed by a proactive model
of what is going on around me
um
I'm very constrained very much
constrained by the statistics I have of
the thing I have seen around me
so regularities Drive Hawaii pay
attention which Drive implicitly or
specifically value and normativity
and you cannot demical steps you can add
reflexivity you can add I don't do
accountability you can add a lot of
things but you cannot remove the very
basic way in which cultural values and
transportation are embedded in
perception
so um
yes this is a repetition of what I said
the patterns in the flow of attention
that are embedded that I have developed
through the very fact of engaging with a
cultural niche and they constrain my
actions towards specific outcome they
entail specific values specific norms
and they entail
um at least they constrain very very
very very very heavily the intention
that I'm even able to conceive to
generate
so
there is a dual Liberation equivalent
way to see this which is uh engagement
with the social landscape so every agent
they experience the world not in the
same way of course but the experience
the same
let us say that each person this kind of
the world it's predicts very strongly
the experience of the world that other
people we develop around them
so they are structural properties of the
you know landscape
of opportunities and perception and
possible action that we experience there
are properties that are transferred
between individuals robustly this is the
case for example of norms so if I say if
I say um
if I look at the law any specific law
all of the people in the same country
they are subjected to the same law so
maybe some of them can just ignore it
they live too far from the city we don't
have cops here maybe some of them are
above the low in some capacity of their
relation but the basic constraints that
the low entire it is experienced by
everyone in a different way we all
expect that specific people will react
to specific situations in specific way
and this is a special property of the
landscape that we experience
so
the
way that these landscape shapes
expectation in a robust way we can look
at basically it's as a constraint so not
as a iterative property of a landscape
that I can or cannot experience but just
as a statistical
force that shapes behavior in a specific
way
and looking at things like that it means
that I can see uh given social cultural
feel in two complementary way as a set
of agents that navigates uh common well
not quite common but
mutually constrained social control
worlds or as a set of constraints that
produce itself and the way agents
reconstructs the world around them in
their mind the way they understand it
you know you know creative manner it is
equivalent to the way the set of
constraints reconstructs itself
which is important because if I can
reconstruct if I can look at this real
world as a set of constraints over
statistical constraints for behavior
that reproduce itself I can look at it
as a living thing strictly speaking
because this is how we Define living
things at least in
specific sub-branch of system biology
that I believe is relevant is to be
believed about that
so when we talk about structural
landscape we can look at them either as
a landscape of affordances this is
opportunity for Action that are
experienced and enacted by a set of
individual agents which interacts so as
to having some level of coherence
between the Landscapes they um
experience Linux and I can look at the
same landscape as a system of
constraints that are exerted over the
behavior of this agents
and that I can Define and study with no
play reference to any individual agent
in the same way that I can study a I
don't know dog without looking at every
single individual cell what you're
interested in biology or sociology is
usually you know aggregated patterns not
what every single living thing around
thinks of every single thing
so
that was the heaviest it got I uh
probably over the world course
I
do not expect you to grasp all of the
consequences of what I said because it
was very condensed
and it was very abstract but the case
I'm making here is not that everyone has
to understand all the math right now it
is
uh that's this framework it does things
to say about relevant question in social
science
and to make this point I will not just
you know give the abstract presentation
of how it's awesome because we have
landscape what not I will look at
specific Fields questions case studies
in Social sense
and I will look at basically how
actually in France entails a pretty
specific model of that
let's see as well grounded in
commutative sense and that is relevant
and that is adequate to the study of
living changing systems etc etc
so
first I join us a team
some of you will know what it is some of
you will not know what it is
so
um
address I think is something that is
situated in the work on public opinion
specifically like we
I believe this book is called public
opinion
um so another setting it refers
historically also you have more diverse
way to understand it now to the role of
mass media like journals and later TV in
manufacturing consent this is a textual
station from the text
of
um no I thought in the book cover I
forgot the name of the guy I'm sorry you
have to look at the reference but it is
um
used to study how mass media can
manifest manufacture consent by drawing
attention to specific issues and shaping
specific expectations about the world so
the idea is that you have a role an
active role of the elites what they call
the elites here people which have
outsized inference of the flow of policy
or Society I will call them Elite and so
those people they basically transmit
Norms like transmit non-native
expectation uh so consent to whatever is
the thing that they do that they want
you to do more specifically
and I do so not by telling you uh do
this and that they do so by building
agendas so drawing attention to specific
issues in specific way
and you can see here people who are I
mean it's prevalent in political like
horrendous that but the U.S right wing
is very very very um transparent in
doing that and so this is a meeting
between two experts in Azure setting
with Donald Trump and run the sentis
which
um
basically I've convinced people that
they should not worry about things like
that I don't know the price of life
whether we wage war here and there uh
why do we have to pay millions why do
U.S people have to pay millions to get
Healthcare but to how lgbtq democratic
people
threaten the US life in a very abstract
way like a
did not ever hear any consistent
coherent believable mechanism by which
they explained how lgbtq threatens
whatever Republicans
uh but they do draw attention to this
topic they do share this rotation that
Democrats and gbtq are collectors and
they do so in a way that is able to
legitimize
themselves as become other people to
mobilize people to actually you know be
behind them and do their bidding and to
colonize political life in a way that is
convenient for them because it you know
keeps any power
and the role of attention uh the way you
pay attention to things
in shaping Behavior it's just a redo of
what I explained in um in active
inference if you believe that the way we
the force is the way we constrain
attention is applicative of behavior
then you believe in actual inference
just Express differently so this is a
case where you have a classical let us
say concept industrial sense that
essentially reduces to concepts of
active inference it's not to say of
course that sociology is a relevant and
we should just do cognitive sense but
this is pretty rare to have such a
direct response between topics that are
disciplinary this far apart so all this
is something we should definitely pay
attention to
so uh second case study nationalism
um basically this case study is entailed
by what I said over the Republicans
because we move by which they legitimize
their rule it is just say we have we
share an identity here um U.S
conservative Traditional Values etc etc
and this identity it entails specific
norms and for reasons that
we originally left out of
the frame I so Elite people run the
scientist Trump Napoleon or whatever I
get to tell you what this energy entails
in terms of behavior you don't get to
speak really because you know you are
not someone who has a newspapers that
para today say you know what you say
because you have to keep on doing this
subject
and this is very consistent with
Dynamics by which we constructed nation
states so for the uh historical context
the idea that we have ethnicities
and this is somehow relevant normatively
like this love should organize together
or the uh I don't know uh hungarians
together and we should get to agree to
things that we do and then do them it's
very recent
um it's extremely recent dates
well I won't get into the specifics but
let us say in this specific formulation
it dates from the 19th century uh when
you add a bunch of very poor
photographic Administration that took
hold respectively of
France United Kingdom uh crucial and
they are the capability to rule most of
these social activities
but they did not have any clear argument
why people should you know listen to
them in any capacity
and the way it um
it worked is that those Administration
they
basically started claiming that there
were some representative of a given uh
ethnical and linguistic community
and that in virtue of being part of this
community you should listen to them and
uh pay them respect and actively work
for their goal to be fulfilled
and of course it is not that easy to
make this claim but what happened is
they
invested a huge deal of inner
generalization into actually having
people buy that they built schools a
little prison they built a psychiatric
hospital they built a lot of
infrastructure that enabled them to
transmit Norms in a very robust way and
transmit identity in a very robust way
and in doing that they managed to embed
most of the micros relation you could
have into their specific
ethnicity and into the normative power
they lend to this ethnicity so at some
point you were you know
um I always forget farmer in uh lost
Village in France you only meets
menstruation at tax time so main arm
come and tell you give your grain and
you give your brain because that's your
dad and at some point those people send
you a teacher and they send you
newspaper and they claim hey you are
French you have to speak French you have
to be friends with us you have to fight
our Wars and because there is so much
you know uh energy that is pending that
people actually bite or die that's
another option because you know uh the
uh
other side of the coin is that
um
states that legitimate themselves
through a nationhood they are basically
to be all the time
invested in at Nicole cleansing because
people who are not the right ethnicity
they are not
considered element of these states so
they have to be submitted or removed
which is a bad thing to do this is very
bad thing to do when you can see
and
um I like I'd like to illustrate this
whole notion of energy capture through
the African Renaissance monument that
Abdullah wait uh so the president of
Senegal had constructed in uh in the
capital so it's very glorious it it is
very um
good example of identity capture because
it shows you uh the Norms it shows your
glorious image of the African
man and it shows how you have to you
know
be supportive of children show them
protect them with your big muscle and
give them very well ambition while
African women look at you like they were
um
non-agents let us say that so it gives a
blueprint around which society should be
organized
it gives you a very specific
picture of who this is speaking to in
this case Africans because I guess
Senegal gets to say what is good for
Africa that is
um coherent claim to make I mean
sarcastic sorry
and why I like this specific Monumental
you have lots lots well first it's very
expressive you don't you're the auditory
of in France it serves the basics and
function but it's not it does not show
you it tells you and the afghanistani
shows you what it means
in a very uh well obvious way and the
second main reason is this
uh you have nothing around it they just
put it in a pile of dirt and I invest in
nothing in the infrastructure because
they were too busy you know keeping
taking money from themselves I guess I
don't know exactly what who I did with
tax money but clearly it was more
invested in the symbolism of what
African men should do and why they
should follow him specifically and not
in concrete infrastructure and
in most cases energy capture is very
radial for people who are you know
captured this is why I call that capture
because uh what you get out of energy
capture is a
symbolic sense of being part of the good
team and what you have to give is
usually you know the entirety of the
work you do over your life
uh it gets
given to the state Administration that
wants you to do things and yeah you do
things for them and
sometimes they build infrastructure but
if they don't want to they will not that
is very very very very much a bad deal
and I uh I give it away so National
entity it was diffused to a school and
mass media it was embedded in a micro
networks of solidarity so typically the
African resource Monument it gives you
basically tells you that as a huge bond
in fatter you have to give in whatever
the state analogy of what uh was and
then it is leverage for mobilization and
legitimation and control
and you have another
that's that's not
um oh I did not say why it was relevant
to a team friends well it is relevant to
active in France because all this is
mediated by self model all of this is
enabled because people have self model
and they enact the self model
and there is no necessity of a reflexive
step where you actually you know think
about what is yourself model and oh you
are expected to do a thing you do the
thing because you expect yourself to be
doing the thing and relaxing in France
as we said you do what you expect to do
so this basically explains why such
symbolic you know raw power it has
actual consequences well if you have uh
you know more rational model of humanity
the question is hey why you build big
things and not uh infrastructure it
would be a rational response but this is
not what people do people follow norms
and this is a way to broadcast Norms
very efficiently and robustly
so uh due to that I'd like to talk about
structural agency so there is a constant
question in a social sense usually
social sense talk about you know
structure so Norms habitus uh way that
institution builds through life
and there is a legitimate question that
is asked
um
which is if you believe structural
treatment Behavior what is the place for
agency so there is there are constant
debates in every field possible of
social sense regarding what is actually
explained by the structure and what is
left to individual agency and what I
want to say is that this question is
especially dissolved by the model of
agency we have
so
as we said uh agencies exerted through
expectation over myself
so because social structure it becomes
expected it is enacted through the LMC
of these specific people that are within
it not have an opposition between
how strong the institutions are and how
adjunctive people are because strong
institutional institutions that
basically become embedded in yourself
model and so are
um you know there are people freely not
freely it's a matter but
from their own accord they enactose
institution and this is the whole thing
about anti-capture which I presented
nationalistic ideology is strong is
efficient in building actual
mobilization because it makes you
believe that you will actually if you
want a court follow the uh
um social order it gives which will
which was often presented but pretty
rare in a pre-modern institution usually
from the institution are
um I am a king I have an army give me
food
and when you have legitimation attempts
to actually explain why I should get the
food
um these are pretty much justification
this is the elite people talking to
themselves about what why the
objectified knowing that
but you have no arguments and you have
that would be actually compelling so as
to why you would have to give the food
and you have no attempt whatsoever to uh
convince people who have to give the
food they should give the food the
psychology is not they do not talk to
the people they ask things from they
talk to themselves about why they have
they can't they are legitimate to take
those things
and so yeah in the in those uh case you
have a pretty evident controlling
between structure and agency do I uh do
what I'm told to do on their set of
death or do I do any other thing of
course most people would like to do
other thing but they can't and I will
feel or they can't
but if you accept that agency is built
through normativity through engagement
with a social cultural field of finances
Authority for action
yeah you have to admit that software
exists at least in part through agency
because what agent believe is legitimate
what agents believe is right what I
don't believe is expected
it is very precisely what considered
sutures
and that is a
Insight that is as at least in partly in
of the conversation in in some killer
I'd like to um
to show why it's
um the direct conflict between certain
agencies it does not have a strong
running
uh uh yes again I have said the thing
that the slide would say
there is another thing that is maybe
closer to my core body of work which is
uh how active in France afford
indirectly an archeology of an interview
landscape
so
um
if such organization is made of
constraint or behavior
and those constraints are to some extent
embedded in the natural environment of
the people then we count to some extent
study
archaeological landscape for themselves
we can look at the landscape like
material landscape the
um objective study of archeology and we
can make some inference over the
constraints that this landscape entails
of our Collective Behavior
uh I will not get into detail so as to
why because it's um
it's uh Farkle making this inferences
difficult but very concretely we can ask
how
whether you're okay so
daddy that some people get to say to
other people what to do and
certification really that some people
are
by nature or both other people uh there
can be a very vertical patterning so you
have a claim by um people who fund me
escape projects look it up it's nice
you have a claim that
to some extent
the rectification of society around the
Iron Age it is written it is embedded in
vertical patterns in material culture
and architecture and
maybe I will not buy the claim outright
but it is very compelling if you look at
specific architecture you get a specific
feeling so this is the um not cathedral
but maybe basilic or free catic I will
not try to say the name because I do not
speak Icelandic and that would be bad
but you are very Progressive compelling
curve throughout the sky it was a
specific feelings that are
um how do you say produced by this
architecture and you have a very
specific way
in which drives attention from some
something wide on the ground to
something that goes up
and if I did not make it clear yet if we
buy it in France we buy that the
patenting of attention uh the way you
give attention to things it carries
Norms it carries intentionality
and in first person by introspection you
can I think all of you can very clearly
see how architecture it drives specific
patterns of attention
and how those pattern specific elicit
specific feelings
and we currently do not have models that
would be very specific and reproductive
of how this work but we could this is
this is usual but this is doable work
this is not speculations and I do not
know further communism but actually in
France that would actually make it
possible
and last I'd like to uh talk about
um
uh the world's work my favorite thing in
Social sense I guess which is a single
state Scots anthropology of states
so the core argument of Scots I'd say
it's hard to identify a core argument in
that book but
you have ways in which states so here
equivalent to administrations they
understand the world and some world
through you know written forms then they
can pass around uh many people one
institution to have actually a coherent
model of the world but he's
that is pretty much obvious and what
should be obvious but is not is that
those models are reductive in the sense
any model are they emphasize specific
information and they live out
other specific information
and something that is very interesting
I'd say is that states they tend to push
specific models specific Landscaping
specific Norms in urbanism specific
family norms the build eligibility so
the ability to be understood by the
state
so for example
uh you could have you could have very
sparse settlements that are quite
autonomous and that do the thing it is a
possibilities yeah there is no law or
physical constraint to run that but it
is far easier as a state to manage what
is very close to it right so for a state
it's good to have you know a population
that lives very close to a center of
power
because those people they are just there
you can go tell them what to do it's
simple
and you can you can go ask them things
it's simple too it's very easy to manage
that
and a lot of people they would need you
know food to stay there
so we need some kind of
food production model that is easy to
take from that is easy to organize and
engulge as a centralized Institution
and this is monoculture this is
agriculture as we understand it
currently this is people I think Big
Field that make the same crop always
cereals well not always sometimes
potatoes but mostly cereals because
Heroes you know it's very dense
energetically it is easy to keep
it's easy to transport because it is
dense and it is it's Day Edible long
after
you know
recalled user recalls English crop
cropping I don't know what is the word
but when you take the food from the
plants
and people have to stay there for very
long to cultivate that so they cannot
you know go around and put potatoes here
and there and leave when they don't so
you can just go to people and you know
where the people are and where you can
take the food
and uh you know when the food is going
to be um to be
again I don't know the word cropped
because materials it's always at the
same time it's very visible in the
landscape uh how far you are from uh
resulting slash cropping so you cannot
really have a way to cheat that you can
just send many nerves take the food
give it to the city to Japan population
and you have a very um rationalized
controllable Society
and
we we do not know that this is the
reason why we have cities and uh
monoculture but we do have traces that
states very consistently try to have big
cities and more cultural field
and mostly they succeeded
and oh yeah this is relevant to active
in France because inactive in France the
way you pay attention to things it is
productive of your world it is
productive of what cognition you have
and here the capacity for administration
the capacity for written symbols that
tell what things are they are critical
to States understanding of the world
they are
what literally produces the way they
States pay attention to things
and in fact it wasn't
basically major thing for them to have a
world that looks like this it is uh very
directly telling about you know
the fact it creates a world it's a
direct institution of that and that is a
nice thing to do and I'm happy I did
this link
so this is for the case studies uh
uh expectedly you don't see the
collections not all of them maybe you're
convinced that there is something there
but most likely you don't see very
precisely what is to be seen here
so the expectation is that over the
course you develop a very specific
understanding of active inference the
framework
uh you develop a specific understanding
of how it relates to social science to
questions that are relevant instruments
and we develop the capacity to know of a
informal opinion that's critical inform
opinion on how this relates to question
in true science
so
uh we are doing the introduction lecture
hopefully I have convinced you there is
something to see here if not too bad
uh and the next session will be in four
days not one week four days it will be
about
um basically the basics of action France
what you have to know to understand
not the framework per C because it's
math heavy but what the framework says
about all life as cognitive agents
so then you have the discussion I
you should know that for each lecture
there is discussion lecture is a you
know vertical people told you listen
discussion is more free form uh every
person has a magically Authority on how
they share the discussion but the
expectation is that it is a discussion
because it's the name we gave to the
thing
so after the basics we'll look at
patterns of collective Behavior so how
those elements on the cognition human
combination are non-efficient they give
tools to study the organization of
collective systems like and colonies our
societies but we'll stay in um not
specific to human approach we'll be
interested in Collective Behavior but
we're not interested in the specific
patterns of collective Behavior as
afforded by a human condition
they will look at semantics and
semantics the evolution of symbols so
things that are closer to humans we look
at how at in France accounts for
evolution of symbol and what evolution
of symbol affords for commission and
then from here we look at various
efficiency things Norm script narrative
language so how
thesis cushion on active inference and
Collective behavior and semitics they
inform very directly they give a model
specific principled predictive model of
social human behavior and then we look
at so my thing the way I like to think
of it all which is show constraints and
we'll go back to the claim that their
Landscapes of social cultural commission
thingy thing and those landscape can be
looked at in uh you know abstracted from
the individual scale Manner and this is
explanatory of control change and then
we go for the conclusion so we're
interested in your opinion of course
this is the first one we'd like to have
feedback a lot of feedback on what you
thought of it and what would make him
good
um
so that will be for the conclusion
discussion
so here I hoped that you would present
yourself uh
we have not the capacity right now to
have um
students tag the screen and talk
but I'd like to know uh you can say in
the chats what is your background what's
our expectation for the course
whatever you want to say about you know
things the world preferably um being
related somehow to the course that would
be nice
uh but yeah please tell things to us
that concludes my talk I thought
these slides but clear
we have uh last thing maybe we
considered making uh projects so you
making projects that we read and maybe
on Thursday grades
but I do not think that we are in
capacity to give you know um
and standardized normalized
degree or at a station that has any
value so we decided not to do it but if
you so asking you to do things uh to do
projects is a bit weird if you're not
gonna you know grade it and attest that
you did it but if you want to do it if
you want to write things and send them
to us for review this is a this is very
okay you can do you can do that you are
not formally invited to do that but you
can do it
well I'll just add a point on that and
then meanwhile if anybody wants to ask a
question live chat
um
we did raise this topic of different
qualifications and it's something that
we've been working on and continue to
work on in The Institute so potentially
in future versions but absolutely in
future offerings we will have these
kinds of courses
but as eval mentioned this is kind of a
first run and so it's really exciting
just to even start that conversation and
and see what people are looking for in
terms of certification
um all right so let's go to some
questions in the live chat and comments
so
oh yeah good um I did not make this
escalation clear but you know because it
is a first and because we are still
checking the course it is
so much more important than you actually
tell us what what you expect out of it
like what you want or what you perceive
will be here you know expecting the
active influence sense that is a bit
perception a bit action please tell us
about that
awesome in fact the only way to reduce
one's uncertainty is through active
engagement and one is literally applying
active inference when they do actively
engage in this epistemic way so
I hope that all comes through all right
a first question from spumato in the
chat does active inference provide us
with predictive power
potentially focusing on human or social
scale issues what does it look like or
where would you say active inference
provides us with predictive power or
unique explanations and predictions
so uh yes or no depending on the
granularity of the question so what's
your look at acting friends and not
active in France
action France is a branch of creative
processing so it's a family in
incognition that's
consider that your perception of the
world is based on prediction you have
two specificity of active inference
within practice processing one
specificity is that
it says that actions are predictive
our base and prediction to the other is
that it proposed basically a
mathematical formalism in which to study
that that grounds the claim but also
constrain the mechanisms a little bit
uh proactive processing as a family is
predictive of um
many things inspective of the fact that
basically you think you see things but
you are not in capacity to perceive them
right now so I see
um
bit of
tissue no fabric that has been my
computer but I know and I see the
patterns in it but I know perfectly well
that they sell that are actually that
have the Precision to see those patterns
they are looking at the screen now so I
cannot possibly know what the buttons
are except if I expect it and this is
what checked my perception so this is
predicted by predictive processing and
what is also operated is that basically
the information flow in the uh
perception part of the brain it is
heavily top down you have more uh
bandwidth that goes from visor cortex to
the retina then reciprocally which is
simply not compatible with the
direct perception uh passive perception
kind of model it is however compatible
with the idea that we predict the
content of you know retail activity and
when uh our prediction is wrong with
then you have feedback you have
a perception error propagation so this
is pure practice processing this is
explained by crazy processing this is
contradictory actively with
most conceivable variants of non-prexic
processing so yeah prex processing is uh
productive and I say it's
not up for debates as I know
active in France it takes in addition
the idea that um
the actions are based on prediction I
do not know what work empirical work
existed
to check whether this is specifically
the case maybe Daniel you know what has
been done about this
complete your answer and I'll give a
thought
okay
so there are considerable empirical
settings that would check that out I do
not know of them so I will not claim
that they exist or do not exist
uh what is important to me is the
mathematical grounding because uh
most model of cognition kind of assume
that we have computational power that is
implemented somehow somewhere by you
know meets and this is
wrong we cannot just suppose that the
big properties that the brain have you
know they must exist somehow somewhere
we have to actually explain it and this
is what the
mathematical formalism behind active in
France friendship principle does it
explains that we should expect a nickel
system to be predictive somehow
and also it is not direct Limited in
math
it is pretty easy to see why the brain
should have a lot of power doing that
because of the you know very heavy tune
power for demicola tune monitors
so but I would not if active influence
is empirically distinct from other case
of practice processing
I am not sure how
I cannot think of an experiment or
empirical observation that definitely
discriminates between Latin France and
none 13 France brexit processing
these things it exists
great thank you well in many ways active
inference is predictive processing with
action
under additional sophistication and
richness supported by the free energy
principle these are technical topics
that we explore in other discussions as
to whether active inference gives us
unique explanation or prediction
capacity one could look to for example
the linear regression or any other type
of statistical framework linear
regressions in and of themself don't
make predictions because you need a
Target to make a prediction about
however given a linear regression model
relating to health outcomes for example
you might use that model to reduce your
uncertainty which is to say have
predictive power about that system of
interest and so in that respect active
inference has been used to develop a
host of unique explanations and
predictions related to a variety of
cognitive and behavioral phenomena I'll
just leave it at that and I'll read some
introductions and such in the chat so
Robin writes hi my name is Robin I work
in digital governance yeah go ahead
sorry
um what makes that I buy it in France as
a mechanical model of human cognition is
that you don't really get uh adaptive
chemical achievement adaptive action
without
some variant of action being predictive
because the default picture would be
that you have to planify a full action
trajectory but there is no computable
way this can be fast enough and robust
enough and not costly enough to
underline adaptive action so you'd be
basically you'd say I have to grab a cup
I would look at the cup see the cup
plentify movements
another movements if something happens
if I was slightly wrong about the
position of the cup
uh uh the algorithm is too heavy for me
to adjust so you'll not be able to
navigate anything ultimate information
or this is changing and we are very good
at navigating things that means
inflation which are changing so until
there is another mechanical model that
predicts you know attuned adaptive
action I will have to buy active
inference
as a model of
of human conditions basically because
the mass and the line is pretty uh
solids in my opinion
yeah it's always a great question is
relative to what
measurements need a comparator and so
active inference with predictive value
relative to
something unspecified doesn't really
make sense but we can evaluate it better
or worse in a certain setting and so
it's important to compare it so I'll
just read a couple introductions
Robin wrote hi my name is Robin I work
in digital governance I've been curious
about applying active inference to the
construction of governance for digital
Commons great kickoff
swamato wrote hi
I've been studying fundamental physics
and now I am doing Clio Dynamics with a
current interest in pragmatist
philosophy I came to discover active
inference and see how to apply it to
cultural evolution
under
says hello
Anthony writes
bonjour
Anthony
writes
background poker player father
entrepreneur very little knowledge on
subject attend cognitive Security in
Davis working on project that active
inference is very relevant to expect to
learn and engage
and Gina writes
hi I'm a biologist and neuroscientist
that wants to understand the theory to
do experiments with the Xscape team
cool well people can continue to add um
introductions or or questions in the
chat Ben if you want to um ask or or
reflect on anything
um
or I'm sure there's more things to to
talk about
yeah I thought that was a fantastic
introduction
some very interesting connections that I
wasn't expecting there um nice to see
manufacturing consent making an
appearance
and a lot that I think I can uh hold on
let me turn on my camera
yeah certainly a lot that I uh want to
pick up on and hopefully
um Circle background to in the in the in
the session that I'll be doing
cool
cool by the way what I wanted to say
earlier and I could check now is that I
believe I believe that manufacturing
consent was a Shamsky thing but it is
not it is a Litman thing which is the
guy that basically funded the the very
notion of public opinion in the 30s in
the book called public opinion the book
is co-authored with Chomsky learner
Chomsky was not
it was maybe eight at the time I very
much doubt he actually did a thing so
I'm sure you have a copy of that book on
my shelf and I'm pretty sure of the book
manufacturing concerned by Chomsky the
expression manufacturing consent is uh
from a 30s book public opinion by Walter
McMahon that for me the whole public
opinion thing according to Wikipedia
they studied not uh well looked for a
specific book that would specifically
will be less public opinion because like
what do we
mean by public opinion I don't know Lord
don't go clearly but maybe something
else goes I don't know
it's created for that I can at least say
it
that's kind of the interesting question
about multi-scale systems and emergence
if we enable or grant that brains can
perceive or do things that a single
neuron can't but that they have a
material relationship to one another
then is public opinion just like a pile
of sand it just represents the summation
of the The Nest mates or does public
opinion represent a singular integrated
unit in its own respect one that might
have to be sampled by investigating the
material constituents but still being
something different from that
I'll just ask go to a question in the
chat or apple if you ever thought
of sand have semantics
I adopted
for an observerance or for itself
sorry does the pile of sand have
semantics for an observer or for itself
good question foreign
but I can put together brain and and
public opinion different coordination
mechanisms but still connected systems
foreign
sense
if the sand is piling up at the bottom
of an hourglass it certainly has
semantics for an observer who knows
about hourglasses
um
Michael says hello haptivist greetings
Michael and asks a question
please further contrast the terms
regimes of attention and socio-cultural
landscapes
contrast as in explaining what the terms
are I guess
yeah how are those terms similar
different
they say I do not see uh basically we uh
we I propose we active Influence People
I did not have the idea uh propose
regimes of attention so specific
patterns in the way you you know your
attention flows
as
an explanatory mechanism let us say what
underlies the experience of cognitive
landscape coincidence
whatever is the array of things that he
was an agent
um experience uh the world and then uh
we activated from people also claim that
the coordination between individuals in
uh you know cultural agency so the way
we co-construct synchronize regime of
attention means that there is a coupling
between the landscape that we experience
so landscape that are constrained in
such a way I will call social cultural
landscape because it's easier than
saying cognitive landscape that are
constrained by social cultural processes
is that satisfying yeah it's great I'll
just give another view on that
a socio-cultural landscape
is something like the ecological
landscape or the actual basis materially
of our system of Interest what we are
studying in sociology
and so it consists of inert objects as
well as animate cognitive entities
whereas regimes of attention refers to
the dynamical patterns of attention
which is to say relevance and salience
for cognitive agents and so the
socio-cultural landscape to use an
example from avils
presentation might include the modified
Niche that includes a monument
and then
a given cognitive agents might when they
gaze upon that landscape
in a in cultured fashion have a regime
of attention such that their eyes are
moved towards the point of a monument
but the regime of attention is modeled
as a pattern of dynamics of a single
cognitive Asians and inactive inference
we model attention as covert or internal
action
I want to add something I use possibly
abuse the term landscape
um
because it has a very specific meaning
slash connotation which is a space that
you can gaze at that this a landscape is
a space that we can gaze at and
um
you if you go to a more mathematical
notion of space you will basically find
very closely the expectation or formal
entitlements but this space represents
the set of possibilities accessible to a
system like that this is all there is to
it
and this is not what the cognitive
landscape is it's not the set of
possibilities that abstractly an agent
could experience it is what an agent
experience is no what it can they can
guys at no
um so this is why the notion of a
landscape is very heavily used it does
not have a clear mathematical meaning
it should have because it has a very
specific one
conceptual meaning that is critical to
the understanding we have of cognition
and that is not afforded by um
set theory so most mathematics we would
use
um the brand of mathematics we teach in
school and the physicists use
most physicists not all physicists
although we consider like waddington's
epigenetic landscape or if we consider
the surface that variational free energy
is optimized on as a landscape it gives
us a lot of really good intuitions it
gives us something to gaze upon as
instrumental modelers
but it is not the same as the
um
landscape of trees even though each one
of those trees might be modeled by an
observer as possessing a epigenetic
landscape or a regime of attention or a
free energy landscape
well if anyone has other thoughts or
questions we can consider them
otherwise uh
just give me a signums I don't think and
everyone has a
H do you see the uh the image yeah
it's small but waddington's landscape
there you go thank you yeah Wellington's
landscape so it is a very old
uh 30s 20s 30s I guess thing in um
evolutionary biology where so Weddington
is let us say the founder of the
Contemporary developmental biology and
the landscape are basically a dynamical
uh
Fitness I do not know how to not sail
landscape that is a problem there are
basically the space in which uh agents
can evolve
the phenotype of the agent can evolve
during its development
and
um this is a very very very
um Grande visual
metaphor symbolism I don't know for the
story of Developmental system so this is
why
we told koflandscape for the gazing and
for this historical grounding of the
developmental studies in biology
and also I literally I'm paid to
landscape biology landscape archeology
so yeah let's overuse it on landscape
that is good for me
cool but it's an example of using our
spatial and embodied experience to to
get a grasp
on different conceptual topics
Ben you have any comments or or I'd love
to hear a little yeah actually ask about
this this image if there's a couple of
words that I was expecting to creep into
this discussion that that did not which
are uh attractors and repellers about
when you mentioned dynamical systems I
wonder if you think these are useful
terms for thinking about because attract
attraction goes very naturally with
thinking about attention and I wonder if
you think this is a useful
um kind of linguistic tool for
visualizing the relationship between uh
social cognitive Landscapes and uh and
attention
um do you see these children trains
diagram now
okay I wanted to add it if there is a
screenshot laying around I wanted this
to be a to ensure so attractors and
repellers yeah I mean with basically
talking Fitness when we're talking
landscape Fitness Landscapes so I guess
it kind of entails the notion of
attractors and repellers uh no there are
many reasons why it stay away from the
mikola systems terminology because well
um
chemical systems I can tell the
preformulation of all possibilities of
the system which I think is very very
very wrong to do for biological system
and social system that are that undergo
uh the evolution and reconstruction
so I stay away from this uh formalism
whenever possible and attractor
technically mean
sub-regions that you cannot possibly get
out
which exists in conservative system
basically but uh in all cases that we're
interested about it's technically not a
tractor
and
um we can't think of it as a structure
at a specific time scale it's okay but
then if we have to uh abuse the
formalism this much why not not use the
formalism that would be my uh flow of
reflection about this terminology so I
understand the tractors as uh states
that have visited more regularly than
others so is there something about that
that's not correct
I will check it out yeah an attracting
set is one that is Revisited but there
are of course many
sub definitions to be more technical
like the attractor is it just the point
or is it the Basin of Attraction but
broadly on a landscape
as things shake out the attractor begets
some states that are Revisited more than
those that are not that's kind of the
tautological definition of the
attracting set
so so uh a director is emphatically
not at least under a standard definition
uh set of states that is visited more
often it is characterized by forward
invariance so the fact that once you're
in you don't get out so an attractor is
a manifold so a Subspace let us say such
that if you're in get out well there is
a busting of Attraction such that if you
get in the Basin you get into the
tractor
so under if you look at stochastic
clinical systems
maybe you will get out because it's you
know a stochastic means with random
noise basically let's say that so if you
are specifically within a stochastic
technical system so an optimical system
per c
um then you can talk of attractor and
think of things that are not actually uh
that do not have this forward invariance
just things that you tend to stay in for
a while once you win but you are not
talking about contractor anymore you are
talking about some other thing the
functionality is foreign
we shouldn't fall down this Rabbit Hole
completely we can talk about this
another time
let me go to another great question in
the chat
Michael says
a philosophical question science does a
beautiful job of describing and building
testable predictions of reality but
underweight subjective experience
human subjectivity arises within
experience of observation
but includes preconditioning as well as
experience how should science informed
observers reconcile the limits of
subjective experience with the limits of
objectification
science build good models good models
are a competent engagement that is
basically it
um so the question of how to build a
sense that is effective to information
Kairos
I will not use the word effective
perceive but
you know that's pretty close and
we'd have to
in principle sense is built to uh create
precise models precise adding does not
create prediction error within a
specific context that is a
um heavily heavily ritualistic and
conservative
and that would be you could criticize
pretty heavily the institution of
science as a truth Seeker normative
thing
but
so you you'd have to have a good level
of Reform to basically enforce a
modeling that are both robust and easy
to transmit socially outside the cast of
scientists so uh Danielle and nine many
other people wrote a paper on
ontology for decentralized science which
speaks to it
and um
yeah so if you get science you get good
models and once you are good models you
can navigate competently but slash and I
don't know but and both what then then
uh band
um you would need a heavy level of
Reform institution of science
to
get this process be more you know
ergonomic efficient compelling and
socially influential and uh yeah I think
it's an important thing to do when I try
to do it so thank you for the question
I'll give another angle on that
Bayesian statistics
qualitatively equates to the explicit
provisioning of our priors and how we
update those prior beliefs as new
observations come in we may have high
attention to new observations and update
our beliefs a lot we may not be paying
to the attention to the new stimuli and
therefore continue our prior belief so
if we're not paying attention it's kind
of like a belief with inertia
that's greater and if we are paying a
lot of attention then beliefs change
more rapidly and trying to capture every
single belief that leads to a research
team whether they're in Academia or not
to carry out interpret analyze and
communicate a certain topic
that is a really far-reaching task
however Bayesian statistics and Bayesian
approaches like active inference
are helping us get a grasp at the
preconditioning that does play an
essential role with ongoing experience
so
the question of how to engage with extra
institutions and norms and practices
is a challenging and ongoing work but in
some ways the formal principles that
help us understand how context and
measurement come together for cognitive
entities and groups those fundamental
principles are being
communicated
maybe also I'd love to hear about what
you're planning to talk about
yeah I'm not sure if I if I uh I'm not
sure if I even fully understand the
question
um
I took it the question just briefly I
took it to be maybe some worry about the
the relationship between the formalisms
and computational models in active
inference and human subjectivity itself
so how do they how do they bridge the
gap of phenomenology there
um
it's a really interesting question I
know that there are some people who
think that phenomenology is human
subjective experience is just going to
have these transcendental aspects to it
that can't be captured
um with by the formalisms
um that's something I won't be talking
about in my session
um
what I will be talking about is um
so some of the so I'm going to speak on
some things that did come up briefly
today
um so many of the readings uh that
feature in my section are uh readings
that will use the term predictive
processing so I was going to say a
little bit quite briefly about how I
think these different
um different slightly different
Frameworks fit together and what some of
the similarities and differences are
I was going to say move quite quickly
and superficially over some of the the
core mechanisms so Precision waiting
predictions generative models
um and then I was the what I'm going to
try and do is
before we go on to the subsequent weeks
where we look at Collective behavior
um Norms normativity social scripts and
things I wanted to try and build up a
nicely layered picture of what it's like
to be an active inference agent in the
world
and so the way I'm going to do this is
by
um swooping over some philosophical
territory so I'm going to look at the
way active inference has
um said interesting things about
philosophy of Mind particularly in terms
of the role of internal representation
um if I have time I'm going to say a
little bit about embodied cognition some
of the four re stuff
um Avo you got it right so it's embedded
embodied enacted and extended and I'm
not going to be able to talk about all
of those but I'm going to say a little
bit about some of them and how active
inference kind of brings interest in
debates in that area out
I'm going to say a little bit about folk
psychology and motivated action so
talking briefly about what agency itself
is for an active inference agent
um and whether it's psychology
folk psychology
it's um it's a kind of propositional
psychology so it's a it's a framework of
propositions that we generally use to
describe and explain human behavior so
it involves uh propositions such as a
desires b or X hopes that Y and it turns
out that this propositional psychology
is pretty good
um for explaining and predicting human
behavior but it's not just say it's a
scientistly persons
philosophers
so do you mean we in the sense that it's
it's a useful framework
um I mean that you should explain what
the term is because uh it's full
psychology is quite specific it's not a
word that is in you know folk psychology
oh okay okay yeah so folk psychology is
just that basically the linguistic
framework we use to describe human
behavior so if I say you know if I want
to explain why
um aval goes to the refrigerator to grab
a beer I would say you believe there's
beer in the fridge you desire a beer and
then on the basis of that you form the
intention to then go to the fridge
um and it's been
the subject of a lot of philosophical
interest because the the kind of
ontological status of those Concepts is
very unclear so it's it's not clear
whether when we use folk psychological
concepts are we saying that those those
Concepts exist in some meaningful way or
are we taking them more or should we
take a more pragmatic approach and say
that this is just instrumentally useful
but we're not actually positing the
existence of any kind of brain States or
anything like that
um and there's been some interesting
work on how predicted processing and
active inference might map onto folk
psychology
um are they in a necessary kind of
tension because obviously with
predictive processing you have
um just a very very limited set of
Primitives with which to describe and
explain human behavior
so I'm going to say a little bit about
that
um and then I'm going to move straight
into talking about phenomenology and
talking about how
um certain aspects of the framework have
been said to underpin certain kinds of
experiences so I'm going to use a case
study of addiction I think possibly
depression but I think I'm going to talk
about addiction and with this case study
I'm hoping to bring out
um kind of tie together all of the
things that I've said up to that point
and some of the things that you've
covered as well
and I should say as well in the
discussion session
um for my section we'll have a special
guest as well so we're going to be
joined by Professor Mark Miller who is
um a prolific author of predictive
process in a neurophenomenology type
stuff he's done some really really
interesting work on happiness and
well-being depression addiction and
really using the active inference
framework in some quite imaginative ways
um and he's awesome in discussion so
um hopefully you'll find the readings
for my section really interesting and if
you do you'll have a chance to
um kind of have a conversation with the
author for those pieces
travel any closing notes
actually influence rules I will say
one short question I just want to get it
on there while we're here Bryn asks
as a psychologist I am more or less in
the business of helping people minimize
their variational free energy and
expected free energy
great profession
but what are the markers of free energy
in the brain or organism is it heart
rate neuromodulation galvanic
skin response cortisol levels Etc I say
the uh closer proxy would be uh so those
prediction error things in the brain
so when we have expectation that our
related to other preparation of these
information the fact the expectation was
variated and this would be the closest
uh proxy to rational free energy
um
I do not think it would be the exclusive
one but it is the main one and you could
I don't think you could make an
exhaustive list basically anything that
is out of order so as to prompt any kind
of response of either you know updating
models or facting on things it would be
a marker of uh well prediction error
which is not quite version for energy
but is also quite not not quite not it's
so far expected free energy
um I have no idea whatsoever I don't
think this framework is uh has made uh
it's connected explicitly to physiology
yet
Am I Wrong Daniel
yeah it's very uh it's very interesting
question and all I will say or all I
feel like I can say on it is um one
thing we're going to talk about in my
session is um
how prediction error is not always a bad
thing so there's a really nice aeon
article that came out fairly recently
about the value of uncertainty
and one of the things I'm going to talk
about is how um predictive processing
has
you know perhaps it can account for
phenomenons such as uh playful Behavior
creativity
um engagement in challenging hobbies and
dangerous sports and things like this
and how we get an account of exploratory
behavior and curiosity which is kind of
rooted in the fact that for for
creatures like we are for active
inference agents um the resolution of
prediction error itself is a good thing
and so in some sense we're always
seeking it out so it's I think it might
be a mistake to kind of in it's very
intuitive to equate prediction error or
free energy with kind of allostatic load
and stress and negativity but actually
it's going to turn out that that's not
the case
yes thank you and I'll give another type
of answer which is variational free
energy and expected free energy our
statistical calculations about
statistical models so bodies don't have
expected free energies models that are
made about bodies can have variational
and expected free energy and so to that
end whatever you put in your model
is either an observable or a proposed
latent hidden state that you didn't
measure and you may find that different
experiential reports or different
physiological phenomena have different
relationships to each other so indeed it
has been explorers for example which
neural firing rates are associated with
surprise or which hormonal changes are
associated with this or that change in
body temperature
when the generative model is made
the deflationary answer is look at the
data and find out which cues you measure
are associated with your calculation of
vfv and efe however I think it's a
little bit of a map territory situation
and one that's going to come up I am
sure many times in our course
great well I'll just remind people to go
to the course website to review the
syllabus and also encourage everybody to
submit questions through the course
website all of the teachers will review
the questions and we'll give the best
answers we can and also please from all
backgrounds we would love to hear your
voice in the discussions so thank you
again Ben avail
see you next week
bye